<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
                  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title></title>
  </articleinfo>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Design
    </para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
  Before you start coding, it's important to lay down all the business
  rules for the application. This section will introduce the
  application's data models and security rules.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Data Modeling: How to choose the data structure for entities and
      relationships between those entities.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Security: How to convert a set of application requirements and
      business rules into security rules for Couchbase Mobile.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
  <listitem override="2">
    <para>
      Develop
    </para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
  The first steps to getting your project off the ground with Couchbase
  Mobile is to use local persistence with Couchbase Lite. Once your app
  is built to save data locally it's very easy to plug in the
  server-side component, Sync Gateway.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Create, Read, Update, Delete, Query: How to use the persistence
      APIs and query language for simple queries and data aggregation to
      perform query operations across different model types.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Synchronization: How to install Sync Gateway on your development
      environment, start the synchronization from the application and
      manage conflicts.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Security: How to add access control rules based on each
      authenticated user and how to add security locally with database
      encryption and offline login.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Integration: How to use webhooks to trigger events on external
      systems and use the Sync Gateway REST API to import data in
      Couchbase Mobile.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
  <listitem override="3">
    <para>
      Test
    </para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
  Before releasing your application you must ensure that the
  requirements set out in the first section of the training are met.
  This section covers best practices to test the functional and
  scalability aspects of the application.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Functional: How to test the security model of the application and
      make changes to the data model and sync function in the final
      stages of your release cycle.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Scalability &amp; Performance: How to identify the test scenarios
      that are crucial to your application and implement them with load
      testing tools.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic" spacing="compact">
  <listitem override="4">
    <para>
      Deploy
    </para>
  </listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
  Deploying to the app stores and to the cloud at once can be
  challenging. This section will walk you through this process.
</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Deploy: How to setup cloud deployment for a staging and production
      environment and how to continuously deploy to the staging servers.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Upgrade: How to perform a database upgrade or schema migration of
      an application that already went live.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      Scale: How to identify perfomance bottlenecks or a steep increase
      in the load and responding to it by using several Sync Gateway
      instances behind a load balancer.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</article>
